0	1.0	South	NNP	B-LOC
1	1.0	Island	NNP	I-LOC
2	1.0	Maoris	NNS	O
3	1.0	less	JJR	O
4	1.0	likely	JJ	O
5	1.0	to	TO	O
6	1.0	specify	VB	O
7	1.0	iwi	NN	O
8	2.0	WELLINGTON	NNP	B-LOC
9	2.0	—	:	O
10	2.0	Census	NNP	O
11	2.0	figures	NNS	O
12	2.0	on	IN	O
13	2.0	iwi	NN	O
14	2.0	,	,	O
15	2.0	the	DT	O
16	2.0	first	JJ	O
17	2.0	to	TO	O
18	2.0	be	VB	O
19	2.0	collected	VBN	O
20	2.0	since	IN	O
21	2.0	1901	CD	B-DATE
22	2.0	,	,	O
23	2.0	show	VB	O
24	2.0	-	:	O
25	2.0	South	NNP	B-LOC
26	2.0	Island	NNP	I-LOC
27	2.0	Maoris	NNS	O
28	2.0	are	VBP	O
29	2.0	less	JJR	O
30	2.0	likely	JJ	O
31	2.0	to	TO	O
32	2.0	report	VB	O
33	2.0	affiliation	NN	O
34	2.0	with	IN	O
35	2.0	a	DT	O
36	2.0	tribe	NN	O
37	2.0	than	IN	O
38	2.0	North	NNP	B-LOC
39	2.0	Island	NNP	I-LOC
40	2.0	counterparts	NNS	O
41	3.0	In	IN	O
42	3.0	a	DT	O
43	3.0	report	NN	O
44	3.0	released	VBN	O
45	3.0	yesterday	NN	O
46	3.0	by	IN	O
47	3.0	Statistics	NNP	B-ORG
48	3.0	NZ	NNP	I-ORG
49	3.0	,	,	O
50	3.0	60	CD	O
51	3.0	per	NN	O
52	3.0	cent	NN	O
53	3.0	of	IN	O
54	3.0	South	NNP	B-LOC
55	3.0	Island	NNP	I-LOC
56	3.0	Maoris	NNS	O
57	3.0	specified	VBD	O
58	3.0	a	DT	O
59	3.0	main	JJ	O
60	3.0	iwi	NN	O
61	3.0	to	TO	O
62	3.0	which	WDT	O
63	3.0	they	PRP	O
64	3.0	belonged	VBD	O
65	3.0	,	,	O
66	3.0	compared	VBN	O
67	3.0	with	IN	O
68	3.0	74	CD	O
69	3.0	per	NN	O
70	3.0	cent	NN	O
71	3.0	in	IN	O
72	3.0	the	DT	O
73	3.0	North	NNP	B-LOC
74	3.0	Island	NNP	I-LOC
75	4.0	The	DT	O
76	4.0	Government	NNP	B-ORG
77	4.0	Statistician	NNP	I-ORG
78	4.0	,	,	O
79	4.0	Mr	NNP	O
80	4.0	Len	NNP	B-PERSON
81	4.0	Cook	NNP	I-PERSON
82	4.0	,	,	O
83	4.0	said	VBD	O
84	4.0	that	IN	O
85	4.0	87	CD	O
86	4.0	per	NN	O
87	4.0	cent	NN	O
88	4.0	of	IN	O
89	4.0	Maoris	NNS	O
90	4.0	in	IN	O
91	4.0	the	DT	O
92	4.0	Gisborne	NNP	B-LOC
93	4.0	area	NN	O
94	4.0	specified	VBD	O
95	4.0	a	DT	O
96	4.0	main	JJ	O
97	4.0	iwi	NN	O
98	4.0	,	,	O
99	4.0	the	DT	O
100	4.0	highest	JJS	O
101	4.0	proportion	NN	O
102	4.0	in	IN	O
103	4.0	the	DT	O
104	4.0	country	NN	O
105	5.0	The	DT	O
106	5.0	lowest	JJS	O
107	5.0	proportion	NN	O
108	5.0	was	VBD	O
109	5.0	54	CD	O
110	5.0	per	NN	O
111	5.0	cent	NN	O
112	5.0	in	IN	O
113	5.0	Otago	NNP	B-LOC
114	6.0	He	PRP	O
115	6.0	said	VBD	O
116	6.0	an	DT	O
117	6.0	iwi	NN	O
118	6.0	question	NN	O
119	6.0	in	IN	O
120	6.0	the	DT	O
121	6.0	1991	CD	B-DATE
122	6.0	census	NN	O
123	6.0	asked	VBD	O
124	6.0	the	DT	O
125	6.0	511,278	CD	O
126	6.0	people	NNS	O
127	6.0	who	WP	O
128	6.0	stated	VBD	O
129	6.0	they	PRP	O
130	6.0	had	VBD	O
131	6.0	Maori	NNP	O
132	6.0	ancestry	NN	O
133	6.0	to	TO	O
134	6.0	which	WDT	O
135	6.0	main	JJ	O
136	6.0	iwi	NN	O
137	6.0	they	PRP	O
138	6.0	belonged	VBD	O
139	6.0	,	,	O
140	6.0	and	CC	O
141	6.0	with	IN	O
142	6.0	what	WP	O
143	6.0	other	JJ	O
144	6.0	iwi	NN	O
145	6.0	they	PRP	O
146	6.0	had	VBD	O
147	6.0	strong	JJ	O
148	6.0	ties	NNS	O
149	7.0	Of	IN	O
150	7.0	these,	DT	O
151	7.0	72	CD	O
152	7.0	per	NN	O
153	7.0	cent	NN	O
154	7.0	were	VBD	O
155	7.0	affiliated	VBN	O
156	7.0	with	IN	O
157	7.0	an	DT	O
158	7.0	iwi	NN	O
159	8.0	Of	IN	O
160	8.0	the	DT	O
161	8.0	remaining	JJ	O
162	8.0	144,351	CD	O
163	8.0	people	NNS	O
164	8.0	,	,	O
165	8.0	78	CD	O
166	8.0	per	NN	O
167	8.0	cent	NN	O
168	8.0	said	VBD	O
169	8.0	they	PRP	O
170	8.0	did	VBD	O
171	8.0	not	RB	O
172	8.0	know	VB	O
173	8.0	their	PRP$	O
174	8.0	iwi	NN	O
175	8.0	,	,	O
176	8.0	13	CD	O
177	8.0	per	NN	O
178	8.0	cent	NN	O
179	8.0	said	VBD	O
180	8.0	they	PRP	O
181	8.0	did	VBD	O
182	8.0	not	RB	O
183	8.0	belong	VB	O
184	8.0	to	TO	O
185	8.0	any	DT	O
186	8.0	iwi	NN	O
187	8.0	,	,	O
188	8.0	and	CC	O
189	8.0	8	CD	O
190	8.0	per	NN	O
191	8.0	cent	NN	O
192	8.0	did	VBD	O
193	8.0	not	RB	O
194	8.0	answer	VB	O
195	8.0	the	DT	O
196	8.0	question	NN	O
197	9.0	The	DT	O
198	9.0	report	NN	O
199	9.0	found	VBD	O
200	9.0	the	DT	O
201	9.0	largest	JJS	O
202	9.0	iwi	NN	O
203	9.0	was	VBD	O
204	9.0	Northland-based	NNP	B-LOC
205	9.0	Ngapuhi	NNP	I-LOC
206	9.0	with	IN	O
207	9.0	92,973	CD	O
208	9.0	members	NNS	O
209	10.0	Two	CD	O
210	10.0	other	JJ	O
211	10.0	iwi	NN	O
212	10.0	reported	VBD	O
213	10.0	memberships	NNS	O
214	10.0	of	IN	O
215	10.0	more	JJR	O
216	10.0	than	IN	O
217	10.0	40,000	CD	O
218	10.0	—	:	O
219	10.0	Gisborne's	NNP	B-LOC
220	10.0	Ngati	NNP	I-LOC
221	10.0	Porou	NNP	I-LOC
222	10.0	with	IN	O
223	10.0	48,525	CD	O
224	10.0	and	CC	O
225	10.0	Nga	NNP	B-LOC
226	10.0	Kahungunu	NNP	I-LOC
227	10.0	in	IN	O
228	10.0	Hawke's	NNP	B-LOC
229	10.0	Bay	NNP	I-LOC
230	10.0	Wairarapa	NNP	I-LOC
231	10.0	with	IN	O
232	10.0	43,614	CD	O
233	10.0	members	NNS	O
234	11.0	Ngai	NNP	B-LOC
235	11.0	Tahu	NNP	I-LOC
236	11.0	was	VBD	O
237	11.0	the	DT	O
238	11.0	largest	JJS	O
239	11.0	South	NNP	B-LOC
240	11.0	Island	NNP	I-LOC
241	11.0	iwi	NN	O
242	11.0	with	IN	O
243	11.0	20,304	CD	O
244	11.0	members	NNS	O
245	12.0	After	IN	O
246	12.0	consultation	NN	O
247	12.0	with	IN	O
248	12.0	iwi	NN	O
249	12.0	authorities	NNS	O
250	12.0	and	CC	O
251	12.0	Maori	NNP	O
252	12.0	agencies	NNS	O
253	12.0	,	,	O
254	12.0	the	DT	O
255	12.0	department	NN	O
256	12.0	eventually	RB	O
257	12.0	identified	VBD	O
258	12.0	82	CD	O
259	12.0	iwi	NN	O
260	12.0	in	IN	O
261	12.0	its	PRP$	O
262	12.0	report	NN	O
263	13.0	Some	DT	O
264	13.0	of	IN	O
265	13.0	those	DT	O
266	13.0	identified	VBN	O
267	13.0	as	IN	O
268	13.0	distinct	JJ	O
269	13.0	iwi	NN	O
270	13.0	share	VBP	O
271	13.0	the	DT	O
272	13.0	same	JJ	O
273	13.0	ancestry	NN	O
274	13.0	and	CC	O
275	13.0	name	NN	O
276	13.0	but	CC	O
277	13.0	are	VBP	O
278	13.0	located	VBN	O
279	13.0	in	IN	O
280	13.0	different	JJ	O
281	13.0	areas	NNS	O
282	13.0	of	IN	O
283	13.0	the	DT	O
284	13.0	country	NN	O
285	13.0	.	.	O
286	14.0	They	PRP	O
287	14.0	have	VBP	O
288	14.0	thus	RB	O
289	14.0	evolved	VBN	O
290	14.0	separate	JJ	O
291	14.0	identities	NNS	O
292	14.0	and	CC	O
293	14.0	separate	JJ	O
294	14.0	administrative	JJ	O
295	14.0	structures	NNS	O
296	14.0	,	,	O
297	14.0	Mr	NNP	O
298	14.0	Cook	NNP	B-PERSON
299	14.0	said	VBD	O
300	15.0	A	DT	O
301	15.0	significant	JJ	O
302	15.0	number	NN	O
303	15.0	of	IN	O
304	15.0	people	NNS	O
305	15.0	were	VBD	O
306	15.0	living	VBG	O
307	15.0	in	IN	O
308	15.0	their	PRP$	O
309	15.0	iwi	NN	O
310	15.0	district	NN	O
311	15.0	,	,	O
312	15.0	with	IN	O
313	15.0	Whaingaroa	NNP	B-LOC
314	15.0	being	VBG	O
315	15.0	the	DT	O
316	15.0	most	RBS	O
317	15.0	regionally	RB	O
318	15.0	concentrated	VBN	O
319	15.0	iwi	NN	O
320	15.0	—	:	O
321	15.0	90	CD	O
322	15.0	per	NN	O
323	15.0	cent	NN	O
324	15.0	of	IN	O
325	15.0	people	NNS	O
326	15.0	listing	VBG	O
327	15.0	it	PRP	O
328	15.0	as	IN	O
329	15.0	their	PRP$	O
330	15.0	main	JJ	O
331	15.0	iwi	NN	O
332	15.0	were	VBD	O
333	15.0	living	VBG	O
334	15.0	in	IN	O
335	15.0	the	DT	O
336	15.0	region	NN	O
337	16.0	—	:	O
338	16.0	NZPA	NNP	B-ORG


339	17.0	At	IN	O
340	17.0	its	PRP$	O
341	17.0	last	JJ	O
342	17.0	ordinary	JJ	O
343	17.0	meeting	NN	O
344	17.0	in	IN	O
345	17.0	August	NNP	B-DATE
346	17.0	Ruapehu	NNP	B-LOC
347	17.0	District	NNP	I-LOC
348	17.0	Council	NNP	I-ORG
349	17.0	considered	VBD	O
350	17.0	an	DT	O
351	17.0	agenda	NN	O
352	17.0	item	NN	O
353	17.0	proposing	VBG	O
354	17.0	the	DT	O
355	17.0	establishment	NN	O
356	17.0	of	IN	O
357	17.0	an	DT	O
358	17.0	Iwi	NNP	B-ORG
359	17.0	Liaison	NNP	I-ORG
360	17.0	Working	NNP	I-ORG
361	17.0	Party	NNP	I-ORG
362	18.0	It	PRP	O
363	18.0	requested	VBD	O
364	18.0	that	IN	O
365	18.0	budgetary	JJ	O
366	18.0	implications	NNS	O
367	18.0	be	VB	O
368	18.0	examined	VBN	O
369	18.0	and	CC	O
370	18.0	a	DT	O
371	18.0	budgetary	JJ	O
372	18.0	outcome	NN	O
373	18.0	be	VB	O
374	18.0	proposed	VBN	O
375	18.0	at	IN	O
376	18.0	last	JJ	O
377	18.0	week	NN	O
378	18.0	's	POS	O
379	18.0	monthly	JJ	O
380	18.0	meeting	NN	O
381	19.0	The	DT	O
382	19.0	resolution	NN	O
383	19.0	before	IN	O
384	19.0	council	NN	O
385	19.0	last	JJ	O
386	19.0	week	NN	O
387	19.0	proposed	VBD	O
388	19.0	that	IN	O
389	19.0	a	DT	O
390	19.0	sum	NN	O
391	19.0	of	IN	O
392	19.0	$58,400	CD	O
393	19.0	be	VB	O
394	19.0	approved	VBN	O
395	19.0	as	IN	O
396	19.0	total	JJ	O
397	19.0	funding	NN	O
398	19.0	to	TO	O
399	19.0	be	VB	O
400	19.0	made	VBN	O
401	19.0	available	JJ	O
402	19.0	to	TO	O
403	19.0	the	DT	O
404	19.0	Iwi	NNP	B-ORG
405	19.0	Liaison	NNP	I-ORG
406	19.0	Working	NNP	I-ORG
407	19.0	Party	NNP	I-ORG
408	19.0	from	IN	O
409	19.0	the	DT	O
410	19.0	1993/94	CD	B-DATE
411	19.0	Resource	NNP	B-ORG
412	19.0	Management	NNP	I-ORG
413	19.0	Account	NNP	I-ORG
414	20.0	Cr	NNP	O
415	20.0	Weston	NNP	B-PERSON
416	20.0	Kirton	NNP	I-PERSON
417	20.0	said	VBD	O
418	20.0	that	IN	O
419	20.0	it	PRP	O
420	20.0	was	VBD	O
421	20.0	his	PRP$	O
422	20.0	understanding	NN	O
423	20.0	that	IN	O
424	20.0	the	DT	O
425	20.0	sum	NN	O
426	20.0	of	IN	O
427	20.0	$30,000	CD	O
428	20.0	was	VBD	O
429	20.0	approved	VBN	O
430	20.0	at	IN	O
431	20.0	the	DT	O
432	20.0	original	JJ	O
433	20.0	meeting	NN	O
434	20.0	with	IN	O
435	20.0	Maori	NNP	B-MISC
436	20.0	representatives	NNS	O
437	20.0	and	CC	O
438	20.0	this	DT	O
439	20.0	seemed	VBD	O
440	20.0	to	TO	O
441	20.0	meet	VB	O
442	20.0	with	IN	O
443	20.0	their	PRP$	O
444	20.0	needs	NNS	O
445	21.0	"	``	O
446	21.0	so	RB	O
447	21.0	why	WRB	O
448	21.0	is	VBZ	O
449	21.0	it	PRP	O
450	21.0	now	RB	O
451	21.0	$58,400	CD	O
452	21.0	?"	''	O
453	22.0	Chief	NNP	O
454	22.0	executive	NN	O
455	22.0	Cliff	NNP	B-PERSON
456	22.0	Houston	NNP	I-PERSON
457	22.0	said	VBD	O
458	22.0	that	IN	O
459	22.0	the	DT	O
460	22.0	Iwi	NNP	B-ORG
461	22.0	have	VBP	O
462	22.0	always	RB	O
463	22.0	wanted	VBN	O
464	22.0	$58,400	CD	O
465	23.0	and	CC	O
466	23.0	that	IN	O
467	23.0	he	PRP	O
468	23.0	had	VBD	O
469	23.0	been	VBN	O
470	23.0	conducting	VBG	O
471	23.0	negotiations	NNS	O
472	23.0	on	IN	O
473	23.0	that	DT	O
474	23.0	basis	NN	O
475	24.0	He	PRP	O
476	24.0	assured	VBD	O
477	24.0	council	NN	O
478	24.0	that	IN	O
479	24.0	while	IN	O
480	24.0	there	EX	O
481	24.0	was	VBD	O
482	24.0	no	DT	O
483	24.0	timetable	NN	O
484	24.0	scheduled	VBN	O
485	24.0	for	IN	O
486	24.0	this	DT	O
487	24.0	programme	NN	O
488	24.0	yet	RB	O
489	24.0	,	,	O
490	24.0	it	PRP	O
491	24.0	will	MD	O
492	24.0	be	VB	O
493	24.0	structured	VBN	O
494	24.0	in	IN	O
495	24.0	such	JJ	O
496	24.0	a	DT	O
497	24.0	way	NN	O
498	24.0	that	IN	O
499	24.0	the	DT	O
500	24.0	Ruapehu	NNP	B-LOC
501	24.0	District	NNP	I-LOC
502	24.0	Council	NNP	I-ORG
503	24.0	will	MD	O
504	24.0	retain	VB	O
505	24.0	control	NN	O
506	24.0	throughout	RB	O
507	24.0	on	IN	O
508	24.0	the	DT	O
509	24.0	basis	NN	O
510	24.0	of	IN	O
511	24.0	actual	JJ	O
512	24.0	expenditure	NN	O
513	24.0	for	IN	O
514	24.0	such	JJ	O
515	24.0	things	NNS	O
516	24.0	as	IN	O
517	24.0	travel	NN	O
518	24.0	,	,	O
519	24.0	land-search	NN	O
520	24.0	fees	NNS	O
521	24.0	etc	NN	O
522	25.0	Council	NNP	B-ORG
523	25.0	appointed	VBD	O
524	25.0	Cr	NNP	O
525	25.0	Joe	NNP	B-PERSON
526	25.0	Murphy	NNP	I-PERSON
527	25.0	to	TO	O
528	25.0	represent	VB	O
529	25.0	the	DT	O
530	25.0	northern	JJ	O
531	25.0	ward	NN	O
532	25.0	of	IN	O
533	25.0	the	DT	O
534	25.0	Ruapehu	NNP	B-LOC
535	25.0	District	NNP	I-LOC
536	25.0	Council	NNP	I-ORG
537	25.0	and	CC	O
538	25.0	Cr	NNP	O
539	25.0	Bob	NNP	B-PERSON
540	25.0	Peck	NNP	I-PERSON
541	25.0	to	TO	O
542	25.0	represent	VB	O
543	25.0	the	DT	O
544	25.0	southern	JJ	O
545	25.0	ward	NN	O
546	25.0	of	IN	O
547	25.0	the	DT	O
548	25.0	Ruapehu	NNP	B-LOC
549	25.0	District	NNP	I-LOC
550	25.0	Council	NNP	I-ORG
551	25.0	on	IN	O
552	25.0	the	DT	O
553	25.0	Iwi	NNP	B-ORG
554	25.0	Liaison	NNP	I-ORG
555	25.0	Working	NNP	I-ORG
556	25.0	Party	NNP	I-ORG
557	26.0	Last	JJ	O
558	26.0	year	NN	O
559	26.0	's	POS	O
560	26.0	power	NN	O
561	26.0	crisis	NN	O
562	26.0	is	VBZ	O
563	26.0	thought	VBN	O
564	26.0	to	TO	O
565	26.0	be	VB	O
566	26.0	one	CD	O
567	26.0	of	IN	O
568	26.0	the	DT	O
569	26.0	contributing	VBG	O
570	26.0	factors	NNS	O
571	26.0	behind	IN	O
572	26.0	continued	JJ	O
573	26.0	lower	JJR	O
574	26.0	than	IN	O
575	26.0	expected	VBN	O
576	26.0	electricity	NN	O
577	26.0	sales	NNS	O
578	26.0	by	IN	O
579	26.0	King	NNP	B-ORG
580	26.0	Country	NNP	I-ORG
581	26.0	Energy	NNP	I-ORG
582	26.0	Limited	NNP	I-ORG
583	27.0	General	NNP	O
584	27.0	manager	NN	O
585	27.0	Peter	NNP	B-PERSON
586	27.0	Till	NNP	I-PERSON
587	27.0	told	VBD	O
588	27.0	the	DT	O
589	27.0	September	NNP	B-DATE
590	27.0	directors	NN	O
591	27.0	meeting	NN	O
592	27.0	that	IN	O
593	27.0	August	NNP	B-DATE
594	27.0	had	VBD	O
595	27.0	turned	VBN	O
596	27.0	out	RP	O
597	27.0	to	TO	O
598	27.0	be	VB	O
599	27.0	a	DT	O
600	27.0	poor	JJ	O
601	27.0	month	NN	O
602	27.0	,	,	O
603	27.0	in	IN	O
604	27.0	spite	NN	O
605	27.0	of	IN	O
606	27.0	earlier	JJ	O
607	27.0	hopes	NNS	O
608	27.0	that	IN	O
609	27.0	an	DT	O
610	27.0	overall	JJ	O
611	27.0	drop	NN	O
612	27.0	in	IN	O
613	27.0	unit	NN	O
614	27.0	sales	NNS	O
615	27.0	might	MD	O
616	27.0	be	VB	O
617	27.0	reversed	VBN	O
618	28.0	He	PRP	O
619	28.0	said	VBD	O
620	28.0	last	JJ	O
621	28.0	year	NN	O
622	28.0	's	POS	O
623	28.0	power	NN	O
624	28.0	crisis	NN	O
625	28.0	was	VBD	O
626	28.0	one	CD	O
627	28.0	of	IN	O
628	28.0	four	CD	O
629	28.0	factors	NNS	O
630	28.0	he	PRP	O
631	28.0	felt	VBD	O
632	28.0	were	VBD	O
633	28.0	behind	IN	O
634	28.0	the	DT	O
635	28.0	drop	NN	O
636	29.0	Last	JJ	O
637	29.0	year	NN	O
638	29.0	's	POS	O
639	29.0	shortage	NN	O
640	29.0	caused	VBD	O
641	29.0	fuel	NN	O
642	29.0	switching	NN	O
643	29.0	and	CC	O
644	29.0	switching	NN	O
645	29.0	off	RP	O
646	30.0	From	IN	O
647	30.0	past	JJ	O
648	30.0	experience	NN	O
649	30.0	any	DT	O
650	30.0	shock	NN	O
651	30.0	to	IN	O
652	30.0	public	JJ	O
653	30.0	expectations	NNS	O
654	30.0	takes	VBZ	O
655	30.0	about	IN	O
656	30.0	three	CD	O
657	30.0	years	NNS	O
658	30.0	to	TO	O
659	30.0	even	VB	O
660	30.0	out	RP	O
661	31.0	The	DT	O
662	31.0	warmer	JJR	O
663	31.0	weather	NN	O
664	31.0	being	VBG	O
665	31.0	experienced	VBN	O
666	31.0	this	DT	O
667	31.0	winter	NN	O
668	32.0	was	VBD	O
669	32.0	also	RB	O
670	32.0	a	DT	O
671	32.0	factor	NN	O
672	33.0	with	IN	O
673	33.0	research	NN	O
674	33.0	by	IN	O
675	33.0	other	JJ	O
676	33.0	boards	NNS	O
677	33.0	showing	VBG	O
678	33.0	a	DT	O
679	33.0	1%	CD	O
680	33.0	higher	JJR	O
681	33.0	average	JJ	O
682	33.0	temperature	NN	O
683	33.0	lowered	VBD	O
684	33.0	domestic	JJ	O
685	33.0	consumption	NN	O
686	33.0	by	IN	O
687	33.0	five	CD	O
688	33.0	per	NN	O
689	33.0	cent	NN	O
690	34.0	in	IN	O
691	34.0	the	DT	O
692	34.0	months	NNS	O
693	34.0	May	NNP	B-DATE
694	34.0	to	TO	O
695	34.0	September	NNP	B-DATE
696	35.0	Tariff	NNP	O
697	35.0	increases	NNS	O
698	35.0	over	IN	O
699	35.0	the	DT	O
700	35.0	past	JJ	O
701	35.0	two	CD	O
702	35.0	years	NNS	O
703	35.0	would	MD	O
704	35.0	also	RB	O
705	35.0	have	VB	O
706	35.0	had	VBN	O
707	36.0	an	DT	O
708	36.0	effect	NN	O
709	37.0	along	IN	O
710	37.0	with	IN	O
711	37.0	energy	NN	O
712	37.0	efficiency	NN	O
713	37.0	campaigns	NNS	O
714	38.0	being	VBG	O
715	38.0	run	VBN	O
716	38.0	both	CC	O
717	38.0	locally	RB	O
718	38.0	and	CC	O
719	38.0	nationally	RB	O


720	39.0	REAP	NNP	B-ORG
721	39.0	calls	VBZ	O
722	39.0	for	IN	O
723	39.0	more	JJR	O
724	39.0	Maori	NNP	B-MISC
725	39.0	input	NN	O
726	40.0	The	DT	O
727	40.0	members	NNS	O
728	40.0	of	IN	O
729	40.0	the	DT	O
730	40.0	Ruapehu	NNP	B-LOC
731	40.0	Rural	NNP	I-ORG
732	40.0	Education	NNP	I-ORG
733	40.0	Activities	NNP	I-ORG
734	40.0	Programme	NNP	I-ORG
735	40.0	(REAP)	NNP	I-ORG
736	40.0	council	NN	O
737	40.0	spent	VBD	O
738	40.0	much	JJ	O
739	40.0	time	NN	O
740	40.0	discussing	VBG	O
741	40.0	ways	NNS	O
742	40.0	of	IN	O
743	40.0	increasing	VBG	O
744	40.0	Maori	NNP	B-MISC
745	40.0	input	NN	O
746	40.0	at	IN	O
747	40.0	the	DT	O
748	40.0	meeting	NN	O
749	40.0	on	IN	O
750	40.0	Monday	NNP	B-DATE
751	40.0	night	NN	O
752	40.0	last	JJ	O
753	40.0	week	NN	O
754	41.0	A	DT	O
755	41.0	proposal	NN	O
756	41.0	had	VBD	O
757	41.0	been	VBN	O
758	41.0	put	VBN	O
759	41.0	forward	RB	O
760	41.0	at	IN	O
761	41.0	the	DT	O
762	41.0	previous	JJ	O
763	41.0	meeting	NN	O
764	42.0	for	IN	O
765	42.0	a	DT	O
766	42.0	Maori	NNP	B-MISC
767	42.0	caucus	NN	O
768	43.0	to	TO	O
769	43.0	be	VB	O
770	43.0	formed	VBN	O
771	44.0	At	IN	O
772	44.0	the	DT	O
773	44.0	meeting	NN	O
774	44.0	the	DT	O
775	44.0	council	NN	O
776	44.0	debated	VBD	O
777	44.0	the	DT	O
778	44.0	form	NN	O
779	44.0	,	,	O
780	44.0	membership	NN	O
781	44.0	and	CC	O
782	44.0	the	DT	O
783	44.0	power	NN	O
784	44.0	that	WDT	O
785	44.0	this	DT	O
786	44.0	group	NN	O
787	44.0	would	MD	O
788	44.0	have	VB	O
789	45.0	There	EX	O
790	45.0	are	VBP	O
791	45.0	four	CD	O
792	45.0	Iwi	NNP	B-ORG
793	45.0	places	NNS	O
794	45.0	on	IN	O
795	45.0	the	DT	O
796	45.0	REAP	NNP	B-ORG
797	45.0	council	NN	O
798	45.0	reserved	VBN	O
799	45.0	for	IN	O
800	45.0	Maori	NNP	B-MISC
801	45.0	representatives	NNS	O
802	45.0	from	IN	O
803	45.0	the	DT	O
804	45.0	Ngati	NNP	B-MISC
805	45.0	Kahungunu	NNP	I-MISC
806	45.0	,	,	O
807	45.0	Ngati	NNP	B-MISC
808	45.0	Tuwharetoa	NNP	I-MISC
809	45.0	,	,	O
810	45.0	and	CC	O
811	45.0	Tamaupoko	NNP	B-MISC
812	45.0	Iwi	NNP	I-MISC
813	46.0	Although	IN	O
814	46.0	all	DT	O
815	46.0	these	DT	O
816	46.0	places	NNS	O
817	46.0	were	VBD	O
818	46.0	filled	VBN	O
819	46.0	at	IN	O
820	46.0	the	DT	O
821	46.0	start	NN	O
822	46.0	of	IN	O
823	46.0	the	DT	O
824	46.0	two	CD	O
825	46.0	year	NN	O
826	46.0	term	NN	O
827	47.0	attendance	NN	O
828	47.0	at	IN	O
829	47.0	council	NN	O
830	47.0	meetings	NNS	O
831	47.0	has	VBZ	O
832	47.0	been	VBN	O
833	48.0	erratic	JJ	O
834	49.0	Ruapehu	NNP	B-LOC
835	49.0	REAP	NNP	I-ORG
836	49.0	Council	NNP	I-ORG
837	49.0	chairperson	NN	O
838	49.0	,	,	O
839	49.0	Tauri	NNP	B-PERSON
840	49.0	Morgan	NNP	I-PERSON
841	49.0	,	,	O
842	49.0	urged	VBD	O
843	49.0	the	DT	O
844	49.0	council	NN	O
845	49.0	members	NNS	O
846	49.0	to	TO	O
847	49.0	ask	VB	O
848	50.0	why	WRB	O
849	50.0	Maori	NNP	B-MISC
850	50.0	were	VBD	O
851	50.0	largely	RB	O
852	50.0	unrepresented	JJ	O
853	51.0	in	IN	O
854	51.0	a	DT	O
855	51.0	region	NN	O
856	51.0	where	WRB	O
857	51.0	28	CD	O
858	51.0	per	NN	O
859	51.0	cent	NN	O
860	51.0	of	IN	O
861	51.0	the	DT	O
862	51.0	population	NN	O
863	51.0	is	VBZ	O
864	51.0	Maori	NNP	B-MISC
865	52.0	His	PRP$	O
866	52.0	questions	NNS	O
867	52.0	included	VBD	O
868	53.0	:	:	O
869	53.0	'	``	O
870	53.0	why	WRB	O
871	53.0	did	VBD	O
872	53.0	n't	RB	O
873	53.0	appointed	VBN	O
874	53.0	members	NNS	O
875	53.0	turn	VB	O
876	53.0	up	RP	O
877	53.0	at	IN	O
878	53.0	the	DT	O
879	53.0	first	JJ	O
880	53.0	meeting	NN	O
881	53.0	?	.	O
882	54.0	Why	WRB	O
883	54.0	have	VBP	O
884	54.0	n't	RB	O
885	54.0	they	PRP	O
886	54.0	come	VB	O
887	54.0	back	RB	O
888	54.0	?	.	O
889	55.0	Is	VBZ	O
890	55.0	our	PRP$	O
891	55.0	induction	NN	O
892	55.0	process	NN	O
893	55.0	culturally	RB	O
894	55.0	sensitive	JJ	O
895	56.0	?	.	O
896	57.0	How	WRB	O
897	57.0	do	VBP	O
898	57.0	we	PRP	O
899	57.0	structure	VB	O
900	57.0	our	PRP$	O
901	57.0	meetings	NNS	O
902	58.0	?	.	O
903	59.0	Does	VBZ	O
904	59.0	REAP	NNP	B-ORG
905	59.0	have	VB	O
906	59.0	a	DT	O
907	59.0	welcoming	JJ	O
908	59.0	atmosphere	NN	O
909	60.0	?	.	O
910	61.0	What	WDT	O
911	61.0	protocols	NNS	O
912	61.0	are	VBP	O
913	61.0	in	IN	O
914	61.0	place	NN	O
915	62.0	?	.	O
916	63.0	The	DT	O
917	63.0	council	NN	O
918	63.0	will	MD	O
919	63.0	meet	VB	O
920	63.0	once	RB	O
921	63.0	more	RB	O
922	63.0	before	IN	O
923	63.0	its	PRP$	O
924	63.0	Annual	NNP	B-DATE
925	63.0	General	NNP	I-ORG
926	63.0	Meeting	NNP	I-ORG
927	63.0	on	IN	O
928	63.0	26	CD	B-DATE
929	63.0	April	NNP	I-DATE
930	64.0	and	CC	O
931	64.0	Maori	NNP	B-MISC
932	64.0	representation	NN	O
933	64.0	will	MD	O
934	64.0	once	RB	O
935	64.0	again	RB	O
936	64.0	be	VB	O
937	64.0	on	IN	O
938	64.0	the	DT	O
939	64.0	agenda	NN	O
940	65.0	Early	JJ	O
941	65.0	Childhood	NNP	B-ORG
942	65.0	group	NN	O
943	65.0	may	MD	O
944	65.0	end	VB	O
945	66.0	Early	JJ	O
946	66.0	*	:	O
947	66.0	childhood	NN	O
948	66.0	education	NN	O
949	67.0	came	VBD	O
950	67.0	under	IN	O
951	67.0	scrutiny	NN	O
952	67.0	at	IN	O
953	67.0	last	JJ	O
954	67.0	week	NN	O
955	67.0	's	POS	O
956	67.0	meeting	NN	O
957	67.0	of	IN	O
958	67.0	the	DT	O
959	67.0	Ruapehu	NNP	B-LOC
960	67.0	Rural	NNP	I-LOC
961	67.0	Education	NNP	I-ORG
962	67.0	Activities	NNP	I-ORG
963	67.0	Programme	NNP	I-ORG
964	67.0	Inc	NNP	I-ORG
965	67.0	(REAP)	NNP	I-ORG
966	68.0	Currently	RB	O
967	68.0	three	CD	O
968	68.0	of	IN	O
969	68.0	the	DT	O
970	68.0	REAP	NNP	B-ORG
971	68.0	council	NN	O
972	68.0	members	NNS	O
973	68.0	combine	VBP	O
974	68.0	with	IN	O
975	68.0	REAP	NNP	B-ORG
976	68.0	early	JJ	O
977	68.0	childhood	NN	O
978	68.0	workers	NNS	O
979	68.0	and	CC	O
980	68.0	representatives	NNS	O
981	68.0	from	IN	O
982	68.0	the	DT	O
983	68.0	region	NN	O
984	68.0	's	POS	O
985	68.0	playcentres	NNS	O
986	68.0	,	,	O
987	68.0	kindergartens	NNS	O
988	68.0	,	,	O
989	68.0	kohanga	NN	O
990	68.0	reo	NN	O
991	68.0	,	,	O
992	68.0	preschool	NN	O
993	68.0	and	CC	O
994	68.0	child	NN	O
995	68.0	care	NN	O
996	68.0	facilities	NNS	O
997	68.0	to	TO	O
998	68.0	form	VB	O
999	68.0	the	DT	O
1000	68.0	REAP	NNP	B-ORG
1001	68.0	Early	NNP	I-ORG
1002	68.0	Childhood	NNP	I-ORG
1003	68.0	Education	NNP	I-ORG
1004	68.0	sub-committee	NN	O
1005	69.0	Meetings	NNS	O
1006	69.0	of	IN	O
1007	69.0	the	DT	O
1008	69.0	subcommittee	NN	O
1009	69.0	are	VBP	O
1010	69.0	normally	RB	O
1011	69.0	held	VBN	O
1012	69.0	in	IN	O
1013	69.0	Waiouru	NNP	B-LOC
1014	70.0	but	CC	O
1015	70.0	have	VBP	O
1016	70.0	not	RB	O
1017	70.0	been	VBN	O
1018	70.0	well	RB	O
1019	70.0	attended	VBN	O
1020	70.0	in	IN	O
1021	70.0	the	DT	O
1022	70.0	last	JJ	O
1023	70.0	six	CD	O
1024	70.0	months	NNS	O
1025	71.0	Council	NNP	B-ORG
1026	71.0	members	NNS	O
1027	71.0	questioned	VBD	O
1028	71.0	the	DT	O
1029	71.0	need	NN	O
1030	71.0	for	IN	O
1031	71.0	the	DT	O
1032	71.0	subcommittee	NN	O
1033	72.0	An	DT	O
1034	72.0	early	JJ	O
1035	72.0	childhood	NN	O
1036	72.0	meeting	NN	O
1037	72.0	is	VBZ	O
1038	72.0	planned	VBN	O
1039	72.0	for	IN	O
1040	72.0	Monday	NNP	B-DATE
1041	72.0	22	CD	B-DATE
1042	72.0	February	NNP	I-DATE
1043	72.0	when	IN	O
1044	72.0	the	DT	O
1045	72.0	group	NN	O
1046	72.0	will	MD	O
1047	72.0	discuss	VB	O
1048	72.0	their	PRP$	O
1049	72.0	future	NN	O
1050	73.0	Ruapehu	NNP	B-LOC
1051	73.0	REAP	NNP	I-ORG
1052	73.0	manager	NN	O
1053	73.0	,	,	O
1054	73.0	Marion	NNP	B-PERSON
1055	73.0	Cleaver	NNP	I-PERSON
1056	73.0	,	,	O
1057	73.0	reported	VBD	O
1058	73.0	to	IN	O
1059	73.0	the	DT	O
1060	73.0	REAP	NNP	B-ORG
1061	73.0	council	NN	O
1062	73.0	that	IN	O
1063	73.0	she	PRP	O
1064	73.0	believed	VBD	O
1065	73.0	1993	CD	B-DATE
1066	73.0	would	MD	O
1067	73.0	be	VB	O
1068	73.0	a	DT	O
1069	73.0	busy	JJ	O
1070	73.0	year	NN	O
1071	73.0	for	IN	O
1072	73.0	REAP	NNP	B-ORG
1073	73.0	Assisted	JJ	I-ORG
1074	73.0	Projects	NNS	I-ORG
1075	73.0	(	RB	O
1076	73.0	RAP	NNP	B-ORG
1077	73.0	)	)	O
1078	74.0	The	DT	O
1079	74.0	RAP	NNP	B-ORG
1080	74.0	scheme	NN	O
1081	74.0	was	VBD	O
1082	74.0	set	VBN	O
1083	74.0	up	RP	O
1084	74.0	in	IN	O
1085	74.0	1992	CD	B-DATE
1086	74.0	in	IN	O
1087	74.0	response	NN	O
1088	74.0	to	IN	O
1089	74.0	the	DT	O
1090	74.0	need	NN	O
1091	74.0	for	IN	O
1092	74.0	REAP	NNP	B-ORG
1093	74.0	to	TO	O
1094	74.0	effectively	RB	O
1095	74.0	target	VB	O
1096	74.0	its	PRP$	O
1097	74.0	assistance	NN	O
1098	74.0	to	IN	O
1099	74.0	school	NN	O
1100	74.0	and	CC	O
1101	74.0	community	NN	O
1102	74.0	groups	NNS	O
1103	75.0	In	IN	O
1104	75.0	1992	CD	B-DATE
1105	75.0	$40,000	CD	O
1106	75.0	was	VBD	O
1107	75.0	budgeted	VBN	O
1108	75.0	for	IN	O
1109	75.0	the	DT	O
1110	75.0	RAP	NNP	B-ORG
1111	75.0	fund	NN	O
1112	75.0	but	CC	O
1113	75.0	less	JJR	O
1114	75.0	than	IN	O
1115	75.0	half	NN	O
1116	75.0	was	VBD	O
1117	75.0	allocated	VBN	O
1118	76.0	This	DT	O
1119	76.0	year	NN	O
1120	76.0	Mrs	NNP	B-PERSON
1121	76.0	Cleaver	NNP	I-PERSON
1122	76.0	expects	VBZ	O
1123	76.0	the	DT	O
1124	76.0	full	JJ	O
1125	76.0	amount	NN	O
1126	76.0	to	TO	O
1127	76.0	be	VB	O
1128	76.0	used	VBN	O
1129	77.0	"We	PRP	O
1130	77.0	're	VBP	O
1131	77.0	already	RB	O
1132	77.0	getting	VBG	O
1133	77.0	applications	NNS	O
1134	77.0	from	IN	O
1135	77.0	schools	NNS	O
1136	77.0	who	WP	O
1137	77.0	didn	VBD	O
1138	77.0	't	RB	O
1139	77.0	use	VB	O
1140	77.0	us	PRP	O
1141	77.0	last	JJ	O
1142	77.0	year	NN	O
1143	77.0	.As	.	O
1144	77.0	the	DT	O
1145	77.0	scheme	NN	O
1146	77.0	has	VBZ	O
1147	77.0	become	VBN	O
1148	77.0	better	JJR	O
1149	77.0	known	VBN	O
1150	77.0	more	JJR	O
1151	77.0	people	NNS	O
1152	77.0	are	VBP	O
1153	77.0	applying	VBG	O
1154	77.0	"	''	O
1155	78.0	She	PRP	O
1156	78.0	said	VBD	O
1157	79.0	The	DT	O
1158	79.0	rationale	NN	O
1159	79.0	for	IN	O
1160	79.0	the	DT	O
1161	79.0	RAP	NNP	B-ORG
1162	79.0	scheme	NN	O
1163	79.0	is	VBZ	O
1164	79.0	to	TO	O
1165	79.0	provide	VB	O
1166	79.0	assistance	NN	O
1167	79.0	for	IN	O
1168	79.0	projects	NNS	O
1169	79.0	aimed	VBN	O
1170	79.0	at	IN	O
1171	79.0	improving	VBG	O
1172	79.0	or	CC	O
1173	79.0	enhancing	VBG	O
1174	79.0	the	DT	O
1175	79.0	learning	NN	O
1176	79.0	opportunities	NNS	O
1177	79.0	for	IN	O
1178	79.0	rural	JJ	O
1179	79.0	students	NNS	O
1180	79.0	or	CC	O
1181	79.0	community	NN	O
1182	79.0	groups	NNS	O
1183	79.0	which	WDT	O
1184	79.0	cannot	MD	O
1185	79.0	be	VB	O
1186	79.0	met	VBN	O
1187	79.0	from	IN	O
1188	79.0	other	JJ	O
1189	79.0	resources	NNS	O
1190	80.0	Guidelines	NNS	O
1191	80.0	for	IN	O
1192	80.0	applications	NNS	O
1193	80.0	have	VBP	O
1194	80.0	deliberately	RB	O
1195	80.0	been	VBN	O
1196	80.0	very	RB	O
1197	80.0	broad	JJ	O
1198	80.0	in	IN	O
1199	80.0	an	DT	O
1200	80.0	effort	NN	O
1201	80.0	to	TO	O
1202	80.0	encourage	VB	O
1203	80.0	innovative	JJ	O
1204	80.0	ideas	NNS	O
1205	80.0	targeted	VBN	O
1206	80.0	at	IN	O
1207	80.0	projects	NNS	O
1208	80.0	and	CC	O
1209	80.0	groups	NNS	O
1210	80.0	which	WDT	O
1211	80.0	would	MD	O
1212	80.0	have	VB	O
1213	80.0	no	DT	O
1214	80.0	other	JJ	O
1215	80.0	source	NN	O
1216	80.0	of	IN	O
1217	80.0	funding	NN	O
1218	81.0	Last	JJ	O
1219	81.0	year	NN	O
1220	81.0	80	CD	O
1221	81.0	per	IN	O
1222	81.0	cent	NN	O
1223	81.0	of	IN	O
1224	81.0	grants	NNS	O
1225	81.0	(	(	O
1226	81.0	$14,500	CD	O
1227	81.0	)	)	O
1228	81.0	were	VBD	O
1229	81.0	to	TO	O
1230	81.0	projects	NNS	O
1231	81.0	based	VBN	O
1232	81.0	at	IN	O
1233	81.0	local	JJ	O
1234	81.0	primary	JJ	O
1235	81.0	schools	NNS	O
1236	82.0	seven	CD	O
1237	82.0	per	IN	O
1238	82.0	cent	NN	O
1239	82.0	to	TO	O
1240	82.0	early	JJ	O
1241	82.0	childhood	NN	O
1242	82.0	education	NN	O
1243	82.0	groups	NNS	O
1244	83.0	and	CC	O
1245	83.0	the	DT	O
1246	83.0	remaining	JJ	O
1247	83.0	thirteen	CD	O
1248	83.0	per	IN	O
1249	83.0	cent	NN	O
1250	83.0	to	TO	O
1251	83.0	other	JJ	O
1252	83.0	community	NN	O
1253	83.0	groups	NNS	O
1254	84.0	Applications	NNS	O
1255	84.0	are	VBP	O
1256	84.0	considered	VBN	O
1257	84.0	on	IN	O
1258	84.0	the	DT	O
1259	84.0	relevance	NN	O
1260	84.0	of	IN	O
1261	84.0	the	DT	O
1262	84.0	programme	NN	O
1263	84.0	taking	VBG	O
1264	84.0	into	IN	O
1265	84.0	account	NN	O
1266	84.0	the	DT	O
1267	84.0	needs	NNS	O
1268	84.0	of	IN	O
1269	84.0	the	DT	O
1270	84.0	area	NN	O
1271	85.0	A	DT	O
1272	85.0	panel	NN	O
1273	85.0	of	IN	O
1274	85.0	three	CD	O
1275	85.0	REAP	NNP	B-ORG
1276	85.0	representatives	NNS	O
1277	85.0	meets	VBZ	O
1278	85.0	fortnightly	RB	O
1279	85.0	to	TO	O
1280	85.0	consider	VB	O
1281	85.0	applications	NNS	O
1282	86.0	More	RBR	O
1283	86.0	information	NN	O
1284	86.0	is	VBZ	O
1285	86.0	available	JJ	O
1286	86.0	from	IN	O
1287	86.0	the	DT	O
1288	86.0	REAP	NNP	B-ORG
1289	86.0	office	NN	O
1290	86.0	in	IN	O
1291	86.0	Taihape	NNP	B-LOC



1292	87.0	The	DT	O
1293	87.0	Ruapehu	NNP	B-ORG
1294	87.0	District	NNP	I-ORG
1295	87.0	Council	NNP	I-ORG
1296	87.0	adopted	VBD	O
1297	87.0	the	DT	O
1298	87.0	following	VBG	O
1299	87.0	resolutions	NNS	O
1300	87.0	in	IN	O
1301	87.0	relation	NN	O
1302	87.0	to	IN	O
1303	87.0	the	DT	O
1304	87.0	Ohakune	NNP	B-LOC
1305	87.0	,	,	O
1306	87.0	Raetihi	NNP	B-LOC
1307	87.0	,	,	O
1308	87.0	National	NNP	B-LOC
1309	87.0	Park	NNP	I-LOC
1310	87.0	and	CC	O
1311	87.0	Pipiriki	NNP	B-LOC
1312	87.0	sewerage	NN	O
1313	87.0	schemes	NNS	O
1314	87.0	for	IN	O
1315	87.0	the	DT	O
1316	87.0	1994/95	CD	B-DATE
1317	87.0	Annual	NNP	B-MISC
1318	87.0	Plan	NNP	I-MISC
1319	87.0	.	.	O

1320	88.0	Ohakune	NNP	B-LOC
1321	88.0	The	DT	O
1322	88.0	1994/95	CD	B-DATE
1323	88.0	Draft	NNP	O
1324	88.0	Annual	NNP	B-MISC
1325	88.0	Plan	NNP	I-MISC
1326	88.0	provided	VBD	O
1327	88.0	for	IN	O
1328	88.0	an	DT	O
1329	88.0	estimated	VBN	O
1330	88.0	budget	NN	O
1331	88.0	of	IN	O
1332	88.0	$282,800	CD	O
1333	88.0	for	IN	O
1334	88.0	the	DT	O
1335	88.0	Ohakune	NNP	B-LOC
1336	88.0	oxidation	NN	O
1337	88.0	ponds	NNS	O
1338	88.0	upgrade	NN	O
1339	88.0	,	,	O
1340	88.0	this	DT	O
1341	88.0	sum	NN	O
1342	88.0	being	VBG	O
1343	88.0	made	VBN	O
1344	88.0	up	IN	O
1345	88.0	of	IN	O
1346	88.0	(	(	O
1347	88.0	1	CD	O
1348	88.0	)	)	O
1349	88.0	aerators	NNS	O
1350	88.0	-	:	O
1351	88.0	supply	NN	O
1352	88.0	installation	NN	O
1353	88.0	,	,	O
1354	88.0	power	NN	O
1355	88.0	to	IN	O
1356	88.0	site	NN	O
1357	88.0	,	,	O
1358	88.0	controls	NNS	O
1359	88.0	and	CC	O
1360	88.0	all	DT	O
1361	88.0	fees	NNS	O
1362	88.0	and	CC	O
1363	88.0	(	(	O
1364	88.0	2	CD	O
1365	88.0	)	)	O
1366	88.0	wetlands	NNS	O
1367	88.0	—	:	O
1368	88.0	construction	NN	O
1369	88.0	and	CC	O
1370	88.0	planting	NN	O
1371	88.0	including	VBG	O
1372	88.0	all	DT	O
1373	88.0	fees	NNS	O
1374	88.0	.	.	O

1375	89.0	However	RB	O
1376	89.0	,	,	O
1377	89.0	since	IN	O
1378	89.0	the	DT	O
1379	89.0	initial	JJ	O
1380	89.0	budget	NN	O
1381	89.0	estimate	NN	O
1382	89.0	,	,	O
1383	89.0	consultant	NN	O
1384	89.0	engineers	NNS	O
1385	89.0	Fraser	NNP	B-ORG
1386	89.0	Thomas	NNP	I-ORG
1387	89.0	Ltd	NNP	I-ORG
1388	89.0	have	VBP	O
1389	89.0	advised	VBN	O
1390	89.0	the	DT	O
1391	89.0	following	VBG	O
1392	89.0	reduced	VBN	O
1393	89.0	costs	NNS	O
1394	89.0	:	:	O
1395	89.0	(	(	O
1396	89.0	1	CD	O
1397	89.0	)	)	O
1398	89.0	Aerators	NNS	O
1399	89.0	-	:	O
1400	89.0	supply	NN	O
1401	89.0	and	CC	O
1402	89.0	installation	NN	O
1403	89.0	etc	NN	O
1404	89.0	(	(	O
1405	89.0	$78,000	CD	O
1406	89.0	)	)	O
1407	89.0	;	;	O
1408	89.0	(	(	O
1409	89.0	2	CD	O
1410	89.0	)	)	O
1411	89.0	Wetlands	NNS	O
1412	89.0	-	:	O
1413	89.0	construction	NN	O
1414	89.0	and	CC	O
1415	89.0	planting	NN	O
1416	89.0	including	VBG	O
1417	89.0	all	DT	O
1418	89.0	fees	NNS	O
1419	89.0	(	(	O
1420	89.0	$52,800	CD	O
1421	89.0	)	)	O
1422	89.0	.	.	O

1423	90.0	This	DT	O
1424	90.0	leaves	VBZ	O
1425	90.0	a	DT	O
1426	90.0	total	NN	O
1427	90.0	revised	VBN	O
1428	90.0	budget	NN	O
1429	90.0	of	IN	O
1430	90.0	$130,800	CD	O
1431	90.0	representing	VBG	O
1432	90.0	a	DT	O
1433	90.0	decrease	NN	O
1434	90.0	of	IN	O
1435	90.0	capital	NN	O
1436	90.0	expenditure	NN	O
1437	90.0	(	(	O
1438	90.0	to	TO	O
1439	90.0	be	VB	O
1440	90.0	funded	VBN	O
1441	90.0	by	IN	O
1442	90.0	loan	NN	O
1443	90.0	)	)	O
1444	90.0	and	CC	O
1445	90.0	a	DT	O
1446	90.0	reduction	NN	O
1447	90.0	therefore	RB	O
1448	90.0	of	IN	O
1449	90.0	debt-servicing	NN	O
1450	90.0	requirements	NNS	O
1451	90.0	for	IN	O
1452	90.0	the	DT	O
1453	90.0	project	NN	O
1454	90.0	.	.	O

1455	91.0	However	RB	O
1456	91.0	,	,	O
1457	91.0	it	PRP	O
1458	91.0	was	VBD	O
1459	91.0	pointed	VBN	O
1460	91.0	out	RP	O
1461	91.0	that	IN	O
1462	91.0	local	JJ	O
1463	91.0	iwi	NN	B-MISC
1464	91.0	in	IN	O
1465	91.0	Ohakune	NNP	B-LOC
1466	91.0	were	VBD	O
1467	91.0	not	RB	O
1468	91.0	happy	JJ	O
1469	91.0	with	IN	O
1470	91.0	any	DT	O
1471	91.0	extension	NN	O
1472	91.0	of	IN	O
1473	91.0	oxidation	NN	O
1474	91.0	wetlands	NNS	O
1475	91.0	that	WDT	O
1476	91.0	might	MD	O
1477	91.0	encroach	VB	O
1478	91.0	on	IN	O
1479	91.0	their	PRP$	O
1480	91.0	marae	NN	O
1481	91.0	surrounds	NNS	O
1482	91.0	and	CC	O
1483	91.0	Council	NNP	B-ORG
1484	91.0	were	VBD	O
1485	91.0	advised	VBN	O
1486	91.0	that	IN	O
1487	91.0	the	DT	O
1488	91.0	availability	NN	O
1489	91.0	of	IN	O
1490	91.0	such	DT	O
1491	91.0	land	NN	O
1492	91.0	could	MD	O
1493	91.0	not	RB	O
1494	91.0	be	VB	O
1495	91.0	guaranteed	VBN	O
1496	91.0	if	IN	O
1497	91.0	consent	NN	O
1498	91.0	is	VBZ	O
1499	91.0	not	RB	O
1500	91.0	given	VBN	O
1501	91.0	.	.	O

1502	92.0	Raetihi	NNP	B-LOC
1503	92.0	A	DT	O
1504	92.0	sum	NN	O
1505	92.0	of	IN	O
1506	92.0	$85,800	CD	O
1507	92.0	was	VBD	O
1508	92.0	originally	RB	O
1509	92.0	estimated	VBN	O
1510	92.0	to	TO	O
1511	92.0	be	VB	O
1512	92.0	the	DT	O
1513	92.0	cost	NN	O
1514	92.0	of	IN	O
1515	92.0	upgrading	VBG	O
1516	92.0	the	DT	O
1517	92.0	Raetihi	NNP	B-LOC
1518	92.0	sewerage	NN	O
1519	92.0	scheme	NN	O
1520	92.0	by	IN	O
1521	92.0	the	DT	O
1522	92.0	construction	NN	O
1523	92.0	and	CC	O
1524	92.0	planting	NN	O
1525	92.0	of	IN	O
1526	92.0	sewerage	NN	O
1527	92.0	wetlands	NNS	O
1528	92.0	.	.	O

1529	93.0	However	RB	O
1530	93.0	,	,	O
1531	93.0	consulting	VBG	O
1532	93.0	engineers	NNS	O
1533	93.0	Fraser	NNP	B-ORG
1534	93.0	Thomas	NNP	I-ORG
1535	93.0	Ltd	NNP	I-ORG
1536	93.0	have	VBP	O
1537	93.0	since	IN	O
1538	93.0	re-assessed	VBN	O
1539	93.0	the	DT	O
1540	93.0	upgrading	NN	O
1541	93.0	of	IN	O
1542	93.0	the	DT	O
1543	93.0	Raetihi	NNP	B-LOC
1544	93.0	Sewerage	NNP	I-LOC
1545	93.0	Plant	NNP	I-LOC
1546	93.0	and	CC	O
1547	93.0	recommend	VB	O
1548	93.0	that	IN	O
1549	93.0	an	DT	O
1550	93.0	electric	JJ	O
1551	93.0	motor	NN	O
1552	93.0	be	VB	O
1553	93.0	installed	VBN	O
1554	93.0	as	IN	O
1555	93.0	well	RB	O
1556	93.0	as	IN	O
1557	93.0	the	DT	O
1558	93.0	proposed	VBN	O
1559	93.0	wetland	NN	O
1560	93.0	development	NN	O
1561	93.0	.	.	O

1562	94.0	This	DT	O
1563	94.0	will	MD	O
1564	94.0	mean	VB	O
1565	94.0	an	DT	O
1566	94.0	increased	JJ	O
1567	94.0	budget	NN	O
1568	94.0	expenditure	NN	O
1569	94.0	to	IN	O
1570	94.0	$103,000	CD	O
1571	94.0	but	CC	O
1572	94.0	there	EX	O
1573	94.0	will	MD	O
1574	94.0	be	VB	O
1575	94.0	no	DT	O
1576	94.0	impact	NN	O
1577	94.0	on	IN	O
1578	94.0	rating	NN	O
1579	94.0	requirements	NNS	O
1580	94.0	as	IN	O
1581	94.0	the	DT	O
1582	94.0	increase	NN	O
1583	94.0	of	IN	O
1584	94.0	$18,000	CD	O
1585	94.0	can	MD	O
1586	94.0	be	VB	O
1587	94.0	accommodated	VBN	O
1588	94.0	within	IN	O
1589	94.0	existing	JJ	O
1590	94.0	funding	NN	O
1591	94.0	allocations	NNS	O
1592	94.0	.	.	O
1593	95.0	Pipiriki	NNP	B-LOC
1594	95.0	and	CC	O
1595	95.0	National	NNP	B-LOC
1596	95.0	Park	NNP	I-LOC
1597	95.0	The	DT	O
1598	95.0	original	JJ	O
1599	95.0	budget	NN	O
1600	95.0	for	IN	O
1601	95.0	these	DT	O
1602	95.0	two	CD	O
1603	95.0	sewerage	NN	O
1604	95.0	schemes	NNS	O
1605	95.0	were	VBD	O
1606	95.0	estimated	VBN	O
1607	95.0	to	TO	O
1608	95.0	be	VB	O
1609	95.0	as	IN	O
1610	95.0	follows	VBZ	O
1611	95.0	:	:	O
1612	95.0	Pipiriki	NNP	B-LOC
1613	95.0	(	(	O
1614	95.0	$8,800	CD	O
1615	95.0	)	)	O
1616	95.0	;	;	O
1617	95.0	National	NNP	B-LOC
1618	95.0	Park	NNP	I-LOC
1619	95.0	(	(	O
1620	95.0	$8,800	CD	O
1621	95.0	)	)	O
1622	95.0	.	.	O

1623	96.0	These	DT	O
1624	96.0	figures	NNS	O
1625	96.0	were	VBD	O
1626	96.0	derived	VBN	O
1627	96.0	from	IN	O
1628	96.0	the	DT	O
1629	96.0	estimated	VBN	O
1630	96.0	unexpended	VBN	O
1631	96.0	funds	NNS	O
1632	96.0	carried	VBN	O
1633	96.0	forward	RB	O
1634	96.0	from	IN	O
1635	96.0	the	DT	O
1636	96.0	1993/94	CD	B-DATE
1637	96.0	financial	JJ	O
1638	96.0	year	NN	O
1639	96.0	for	IN	O
1640	96.0	these	DT	O
1641	96.0	projects	NNS	O
1642	96.0	.	.	O

1643	97.0	However	RB	O
1644	97.0	,	,	O
1645	97.0	it	PRP	O
1646	97.0	has	VBZ	O
1647	97.0	now	RB	O
1648	97.0	been	VBN	O
1649	97.0	determined	VBN	O
1650	97.0	that	IN	O
1651	97.0	the	DT	O
1652	97.0	actual	JJ	O
1653	97.0	expenditure	NN	O
1654	97.0	required	VBN	O
1655	97.0	in	IN	O
1656	97.0	total	NN	O
1657	97.0	over	IN	O
1658	97.0	the	DT	O
1659	97.0	two	CD	O
1660	97.0	years	NNS	O
1661	97.0	(	(	O
1662	97.0	1993/94	CD	B-DATE
1663	97.0	and	CC	O
1664	97.0	1994/95	CD	B-DATE
1665	97.0	)	)	O
1666	97.0	is	VBZ	O
1667	97.0	more	JJR	O
1668	97.0	than	IN	O
1669	97.0	originally	RB	O
1670	97.0	estimated	VBN	O
1671	97.0	.	.	O

1672	98.0	The	DT	O
1673	98.0	additional	JJ	O
1674	98.0	amounts	NNS	O
1675	98.0	required	VBN	O
1676	98.0	are	VBP	O
1677	98.0	as	IN	O
1678	98.0	follows	VBZ	O
1679	98.0	:	:	O
1680	98.0	Pipiriki	NNP	B-LOC
1681	98.0	(	(	O
1682	98.0	$2,400	CD	O
1683	98.0	to	TO	O
1684	98.0	make	VB	O
1685	98.0	up	RP	O
1686	98.0	the	DT	O
1687	98.0	required	VBN	O
1688	98.0	total	NN	O
1689	98.0	of	IN	O
1690	98.0	$8,800	CD	O
1691	98.0	)	)	O
1692	98.0	;	;	O
1693	98.0	National	NNP	B-LOC
1694	98.0	Park	NNP	I-LOC
1695	98.0	(	(	O
1696	98.0	$1,440	CD	O
1697	98.0	to	TO	O
1698	98.0	make	VB	O
1699	98.0	up	RP	O
1700	98.0	the	DT	O
1701	98.0	required	JJ	O
1702	98.0	total	NN	O
1703	98.0	of	IN	O
1704	98.0	$8,800	CD	O
1705	98.0	)	)	O
1706	98.0	.	.	O

1707	99.0	However	RB	O
1708	99.0	,	,	O
1709	99.0	once	RB	O
1710	99.0	again	RB	O
1711	99.0	there	EX	O
1712	99.0	will	MD	O
1713	99.0	be	VB	O
1714	99.0	no	DT	O
1715	99.0	impact	NN	O
1716	99.0	on	IN	O
1717	99.0	local	JJ	O
1718	99.0	rating	NN	O
1719	99.0	requirements	NNS	O
1720	99.0	as	IN	O
1721	99.0	the	DT	O
1722	99.0	increase	NN	O
1723	99.0	can	MD	O
1724	99.0	be	VB	O
1725	99.0	accommodated	VBN	O
1726	99.0	within	IN	O
1727	99.0	the	DT	O
1728	99.0	existing	JJ	O
1729	99.0	funding	NN	O
1730	99.0	allocations	NNS	O
1731	99.0	.	.	O



1732	100.0	A	DT	O
1733	100.0	meeting	NN	O
1734	100.0	is	VBZ	O
1735	100.0	to	TO	O
1736	100.0	be	VB	O
1737	100.0	held	VBN	O
1738	100.0	next	JJ	O
1739	100.0	Monday	NNP	B-DATE
1740	100.0	,	,	O
1741	100.0	at	IN	O
1742	100.0	the	DT	O
1743	100.0	Ohakune	NNP	B-LOC
1744	100.0	Primary	NNP	I-LOC
1745	100.0	School	NNP	I-LOC
1746	100.0	,	,	O
1747	100.0	to	TO	O
1748	100.0	form	VB	O
1749	100.0	a	DT	O
1750	100.0	steering	NN	O
1751	100.0	committee	NN	O
1752	100.0	for	IN	O
1753	100.0	organising	VBG	O
1754	100.0	the	DT	O
1755	100.0	centennial	NN	O
1756	100.0	celebrations	NNS	O
1757	100.0	for	IN	O
1758	100.0	the	DT	O
1759	100.0	school	NN	O
1760	100.0	in	IN	O
1761	100.0	1996	CD	B-DATE
1762	100.0	.	.	O

1763	101.0	A	DT	O
1764	101.0	group	NN	O
1765	101.0	of	IN	O
1766	101.0	people	NNS	O
1767	101.0	met	VBD	O
1768	101.0	recently	RB	O
1769	101.0	to	TO	O
1770	101.0	share	VB	O
1771	101.0	ideas	NNS	O
1772	101.0	for	IN	O
1773	101.0	the	DT	O
1774	101.0	celebrations	NNS	O
1775	101.0	,	,	O
1776	101.0	leading	VBG	O
1777	101.0	to	TO	O
1778	101.0	the	DT	O
1779	101.0	decision	NN	O
1780	101.0	to	TO	O
1781	101.0	hold	VB	O
1782	101.0	a	DT	O
1783	101.0	further	JJ	O
1784	101.0	meeting	NN	O
1785	101.0	to	TO	O
1786	101.0	gain	VB	O
1787	101.0	more	JJR	O
1788	101.0	support	NN	O
1789	101.0	.	.	O


1790	102.0	A	DT	O
1791	102.0	Christchurch	NNP	B-LOC
1792	102.0	man	NN	O
1793	102.0	charged	VBN	O
1794	102.0	with	IN	O
1795	102.0	car	NN	O
1796	102.0	conversion	NN	O
1797	102.0	12	CD	B-DATE
1798	102.0	days	NNS	I-DATE
1799	102.0	ago	RB	O
1800	102.0	was	VBD	O
1801	102.0	yesterday	RB	B-DATE
1802	102.0	accused	VBN	O
1803	102.0	of	IN	O
1804	102.0	murdering	VBG	O
1805	102.0	the	DT	O
1806	102.0	car's	NN	O
1807	102.0	owner	NN	O
1808	102.0	.	.	O

1809	103.0	Gregory	NNP	B-PERSON
1810	103.0	James	NNP	I-PERSON
1811	103.0	Toka	NNP	I-PERSON
1812	103.0	,	,	O
1813	103.0	aged	VBN	O
1814	103.0	25	CD	O
1815	103.0	,	,	O
1816	103.0	a	DT	O
1817	103.0	gardener	NN	O
1818	103.0	,	,	O
1819	103.0	appeared	VBD	O
1820	103.0	in	IN	O
1821	103.0	the	DT	O
1822	103.0	District	NNP	B-ORG
1823	103.0	Court	NNP	I-ORG
1824	103.0	charged	VBN	O
1825	103.0	with	IN	O
1826	103.0	murdering	VBG	O
1827	103.0	33-year-old	CD	O
1828	103.0	Brenda	NNP	B-PERSON
1829	103.0	Kingi	NNP	I-PERSON
1830	103.0	in	IN	O
1831	103.0	her	PRP$	O
1832	103.0	Mairehau	NNP	B-LOC
1833	103.0	home	NN	O
1834	103.0	on	IN	O
1835	103.0	October	NNP	B-DATE
1836	103.0	1	CD	I-DATE
1837	103.0	.	.	O

1838	104.0	A	DT	O
1839	104.0	large	JJ	O
1840	104.0	sword	NN	O
1841	104.0	was	VBD	O
1842	104.0	found	VBN	O
1843	104.0	embedded	VBN	O
1844	104.0	in	IN	O
1845	104.0	Ms	NNP	O
1846	104.0	Kingi's	NNP	B-PERSON
1847	104.0	body	NN	O
1848	104.0	after	IN	O
1849	104.0	neighbours	NNS	O
1850	104.0	,	,	O
1851	104.0	who	WDT	O
1852	104.0	heard	VBD	O
1853	104.0	her	PRP$	O
1854	104.0	screams	NNS	O
1855	104.0	,	,	O
1856	104.0	alerted	VBD	O
1857	104.0	the	DT	O
1858	104.0	police	NN	O
1859	104.0	.	.	O

1860	105.0	Her	PRP$	O
1861	105.0	body	NN	O
1862	105.0	was	VBD	O
1863	105.0	found	VBN	O
1864	105.0	in	IN	O
1865	105.0	the	DT	O
1866	105.0	bathroom	NN	O
1867	105.0	of	IN	O
1868	105.0	her	PRP$	O
1869	105.0	ownership	NN	O
1870	105.0	flat	NN	O
1871	105.0	.	.	O

1872	106.0	There	EX	O
1873	106.0	was	VBD	O
1874	106.0	evidence	NN	O
1875	106.0	of	IN	O
1876	106.0	a	DT	O
1877	106.0	struggle	NN	O
1878	106.0	.	.	O

1879	107.0	A	DT	O
1880	107.0	post-mortem	NN	O
1881	107.0	confirmed	VBD	O
1882	107.0	Ms	NNP	O
1883	107.0	Kingi	NNP	B-PERSON
1884	107.0	died	VBD	O
1885	107.0	of	IN	O
1886	107.0	multiple	JJ	O
1887	107.0	stab	NN	O
1888	107.0	wounds	NNS	O
1889	107.0	.	.	O

1890	108.0	Toka	NNP	B-PERSON
1891	108.0	was	VBD	O
1892	108.0	charged	VBN	O
1893	108.0	the	DT	O
1894	108.0	day	NN	O
1895	108.0	of	IN	O
1896	108.0	her	PRP$	O
1897	108.0	death	NN	O
1898	108.0	with	IN	O
1899	108.0	unlawfully	RB	O
1900	108.0	taking	VBG	O
1901	108.0	Ms	NNP	O
1902	108.0	Kingi's	NNP	B-PERSON
1903	108.0	red	JJ	O
1904	108.0	Honda	NNP	B-ORG
1905	108.0	Prelude	NNP	I-ORG
1906	108.0	and	CC	O
1907	108.0	setting	VBG	O
1908	108.0	fire	NN	O
1909	108.0	to	TO	O
1910	108.0	it	PRP	O
1911	108.0	in	IN	O
1912	108.0	Tancred	NNP	B-LOC
1913	108.0	Street	NNP	I-LOC
1914	108.0	,	,	O
1915	108.0	Linwood	NNP	B-LOC
1916	108.0	.	.	O

1917	109.0	He	PRP	O
1918	109.0	did	VBD	O
1919	109.0	not	RB	O
1920	109.0	plead	VB	O
1921	109.0	to	IN	O
1922	109.0	the	DT	O
1923	109.0	murder	NN	O
1924	109.0	charge	NN	O
1925	109.0	yesterday	RB	B-DATE
1926	109.0	and	CC	O
1927	109.0	will	MD	O
1928	109.0	reappear	VB	O
1929	109.0	in	IN	O
1930	109.0	court	NN	O
1931	109.0	in	IN	O
1932	109.0	two	CD	O
1933	109.0	weeks	NNS	O
1934	109.0	.	.	O
1935	110.0	Detective	NNP	B-PERSON
1936	110.0	Sergeant	NNP	I-PERSON
1937	110.0	Phil	NNP	I-PERSON
1938	110.0	Parsons	NNP	I-PERSON
1939	110.0	,	,	O
1940	110.0	of	IN	O
1941	110.0	the	DT	O
1942	110.0	Papanui	NNP	B-LOC
1943	110.0	police	NN	O
1944	110.0	,	,	O
1945	110.0	said	VBD	O
1946	110.0	detectives	NNS	O
1947	110.0	still	RB	O
1948	110.0	wanted	VBD	O
1949	110.0	information	NN	O
1950	110.0	from	IN	O
1951	110.0	anyone	NN	O
1952	110.0	who	WDT	O
1953	110.0	saw	VBD	O
1954	110.0	Ms	NNP	O
1955	110.0	Kingi	NNP	B-PERSON
1956	110.0	on	IN	O
1957	110.0	the	DT	O
1958	110.0	night	NN	O
1959	110.0	before	IN	O
1960	110.0	she	PRP	O
1961	110.0	died	VBD	O
1962	110.0	.	.	O

1963	111.0	"	``	O
1964	111.0	We	PRP	O
1965	111.0	're	VBP	O
1966	111.0	at	IN	O
1967	111.0	the	DT	O
1968	111.0	stage	NN	O
1969	111.0	of	IN	O
1970	111.0	mopping	VBG	O
1971	111.0	up	RP	O
1972	111.0	the	DT	O
1973	111.0	inquiry	NN	O
1974	111.0	.	.	O
1975	111.0	"	''	O

1976	112.0	Several	JJ	O
1977	112.0	police	NNS	O
1978	112.0	last	JJ	O
1979	112.0	week	NN	O
1980	112.0	interviewed	VBD	O
1981	112.0	patrons	NNS	O
1982	112.0	at	IN	O
1983	112.0	the	DT	O
1984	112.0	Alley	NNP	B-LOC
1985	112.0	Cats	NNP	I-LOC
1986	112.0	nightclub	NN	O
1987	112.0	in	IN	O
1988	112.0	Manchester	NNP	B-LOC
1989	112.0	Street	NNP	I-LOC
1990	112.0	,	,	O
1991	112.0	where	WRB	O
1992	112.0	Ms	NNP	O
1993	112.0	Kingi	NNP	B-PERSON
1994	112.0	was	VBD	O
1995	112.0	seen	VBN	O
1996	112.0	alive	JJ	O
1997	112.0	shortly	RB	O
1998	112.0	after	IN	O
1999	112.0	midnight	NN	O
2000	112.0	on	IN	O
2001	112.0	the	DT	O
2002	112.0	morning	NN	O
2003	112.0	she	PRP	O
2004	112.0	died	VBD	O
2005	112.0	.	.	O

2006	113.0	People	NNS	O
2007	113.0	interviewed	VBN	O
2008	113.0	in	IN	O
2009	113.0	connection	NN	O
2010	113.0	with	IN	O
2011	113.0	the	DT	O
2012	113.0	murder	NN	O
2013	113.0	had	VBD	O
2014	113.0	'	''	O
2015	113.0	cooperated	VBN	O
2016	113.0	with	IN	O
2017	113.0	police	NN	O
2018	113.0	.	.	O

2019	114.0	The	DT	O
2020	114.0	police	NN	O
2021	114.0	said	VBD	O
2022	114.0	Ms	NNP	O
2023	114.0	Kingi	NNP	B-PERSON
2024	114.0	was	VBD	O
2025	114.0	"	``	O
2026	114.0	a	DT	O
2027	114.0	friendly	JJ	O
2028	114.0	,	,	O
2029	114.0	likeable	JJ	O
2030	114.0	person	NN	O
2031	114.0	who	WP	O
2032	114.0	was	VBD	O
2033	114.0	well	RB	O
2034	114.0	thought	VBN	O
2035	114.0	of	IN	O
2036	114.0	by	IN	O
2037	114.0	her	PRP$	O
2038	114.0	colleagues	NNS	O
2039	114.0	"	''	O
2040	114.0	.	.	O


2041	115.0	—	:	O
2042	115.0	NZPA	NNP	B-ORG
2043	115.0	.	.	O

2044	116.0	Rain	NN	O
2045	116.0	boosts	VBZ	O
2046	116.0	South	NNP	B-LOC
2047	116.0	Island	NNP	I-LOC
2048	116.0	lake	NN	O
2049	116.0	levels	NNS	O
2050	116.0	.	.	O

2051	117.0	DUNEDIN	NNP	B-LOC
2052	117.0	—	:	O
2053	117.0	Heavy	JJ	O
2054	117.0	rain	NN	O
2055	117.0	in	IN	O
2056	117.0	the	DT	O
2057	117.0	catchments	NNS	O
2058	117.0	of	IN	O
2059	117.0	the	DT	O
2060	117.0	South	NNP	B-LOC
2061	117.0	Island	NNP	I-LOC
2062	117.0	hydro-electric	JJ	O
2063	117.0	lakes	NNS	O
2064	117.0	has	VBZ	O
2065	117.0	helped	VBN	O
2066	117.0	ease	VB	O
2067	117.0	problems	NNS	O
2068	117.0	caused	VBN	O
2069	117.0	by	IN	O
2070	117.0	the	DT	O
2071	117.0	winter	NN	O
2072	117.0	dry	JJ	O
2073	117.0	spell	NN	O
2074	117.0	.	.	O

2075	118.0	The	DT	O
2076	118.0	Electricity	NNP	B-ORG
2077	118.0	Corporation	NNP	I-ORG
2078	118.0	's	POS	O
2079	118.0	communications	NN	O
2080	118.0	manager	NN	O
2081	118.0	,	,	O
2082	118.0	Mr	NNP	B-PERSON
2083	118.0	Bruce	NNP	I-PERSON
2084	118.0	Thompson	NNP	I-PERSON
2085	118.0	,	,	O
2086	118.0	said	VBD	O
2087	118.0	heavy	JJ	O
2088	118.0	rain	NN	O
2089	118.0	in	IN	O
2090	118.0	the	DT	O
2091	118.0	South	NNP	B-LOC
2092	118.0	Island	NNP	I-LOC
2093	118.0	ranges	NNS	O
2094	118.0	had	VBD	O
2095	118.0	led	VBN	O
2096	118.0	to	TO	O
2097	118.0	a	DT	O
2098	118.0	sharp	JJ	O
2099	118.0	rise	NN	O
2100	118.0	in	IN	O
2101	118.0	some	DT	O
2102	118.0	lake	NN	O
2103	118.0	levels	NNS	O
2104	118.0	during	IN	O
2105	118.0	the	DT	O
2106	118.0	last	JJ	O
2107	118.0	few	JJ	O
2108	118.0	days	NNS	B-DATE
2109	118.0	.	.	O
2110	119.0	Lake	NNP	O
2111	119.0	Pukaki	NNP	B-LOC
2112	119.0	,	,	O
2113	119.0	at	IN	O
2114	119.0	the	DT	O
2115	119.0	heart	NN	O
2116	119.0	of	IN	O
2117	119.0	the	DT	O
2118	119.0	Waitaki	NNP	B-LOC
2119	119.0	generation	NN	O
2120	119.0	system	NN	O
2121	119.0	,	,	O
2122	119.0	had	VBD	O
2123	119.0	shown	VBN	O
2124	119.0	an	DT	O
2125	119.0	"	``	O
2126	119.0	encouraging	JJ	O
2127	119.0	"	''	O
2128	119.0	rise	NN	O
2129	119.0	since	IN	O
2130	119.0	Monday	NNP	B-DATE
2131	119.0	.	.	O

2132	120.0	"	``	O
2133	120.0	It	PRP	O
2134	120.0	just	RB	O
2135	120.0	shows	VBZ	O
2136	120.0	how	WRB	O
2137	120.0	fickle	JJ	O
2138	120.0	our	PRP$	O
2139	120.0	weather	NN	O
2140	120.0	patterns	NNS	O
2141	120.0	can	MD	O
2142	120.0	be	VB	O
2143	120.0	.	.	O

2144	121.0	We	PRP	O
2145	121.0	have	VBP	O
2146	121.0	had	VBN	O
2147	121.0	a	DT	O
2148	121.0	significant	JJ	O
2149	121.0	recovery	NN	O
2150	121.0	,	,	O
2151	121.0	although	IN	O
2152	121.0	there	EX	O
2153	121.0	was	VBD	O
2154	121.0	never	RB	O
2155	121.0	any	DT	O
2156	121.0	need	NN	O
2157	121.0	for	IN	O
2158	121.0	the	DT	O
2159	121.0	public	NN	O
2160	121.0	to	TO	O
2161	121.0	be	VB	O
2162	121.0	concerned	JJ	O
2163	121.0	,	,	O
2164	121.0	"	''	O
2165	121.0	he	PRP	O
2166	121.0	said	VBD	O
2167	121.0	.	.	O

2168	122.0	Snow	NN	O
2169	122.0	melt	NN	O
2170	122.0	would	MD	O
2171	122.0	further	RB	O
2172	122.0	boost	VB	O
2173	122.0	lake	NN	O
2174	122.0	levels	NNS	O
2175	122.0	.	.	O

2176	123.0	About	IN	O
2177	123.0	half	NN	O
2178	123.0	the	DT	O
2179	123.0	usual	JJ	O
2180	123.0	amount	NN	O
2181	123.0	of	IN	O
2182	123.0	power	NN	O
2183	123.0	has	VBZ	O
2184	123.0	been	VBN	O
2185	123.0	sent	VBN	O
2186	123.0	north	RB	O
2187	123.0	through	IN	O
2188	123.0	the	DT	O
2189	123.0	Cook	NNP	B-LOC
2190	123.0	Strait	NNP	I-LOC
2191	123.0	cable	NN	O
2192	123.0	each	DT	O
2193	123.0	day	NN	O
2194	123.0	in	IN	O
2195	123.0	a	DT	O
2196	123.0	continuing	JJ	O
2197	123.0	effort	NN	O
2198	123.0	to	TO	O
2199	123.0	conserve	VB	O
2200	123.0	water	NN	O
2201	123.0	in	IN	O
2202	123.0	the	DT	O
2203	123.0	southern	JJ	O
2204	123.0	lakes	NNS	O
2205	123.0	,	,	O
2206	123.0	he	PRP	O
2207	123.0	said	VBD	O
2208	123.0	.	.	O

2209	124.0	Lake	NNP	O
2210	124.0	Pukaki	NNP	B-LOC
2211	124.0	stood	VBD	O
2212	124.0	at	IN	O
2213	124.0	519.85m	CD	O
2214	124.0	above	IN	O
2215	124.0	sea	NN	O
2216	124.0	level	NN	O
2217	124.0	yesterday	RB	B-DATE
2218	124.0	,	,	O
2219	124.0	a	DT	O
2220	124.0	rise	NN	O
2221	124.0	of	IN	O
2222	124.0	16cm	CD	O
2223	124.0	since	IN	O
2224	124.0	Monday	NNP	B-DATE
2225	124.0	.	.	O

2226	125.0	In	IN	O
2227	125.0	the	DT	O
2228	125.0	same	JJ	O
2229	125.0	period	NN	O
2230	125.0	,	,	O
2231	125.0	Lake	NNP	O
2232	125.0	Tekapo	NNP	B-LOC
2233	125.0	rose	VBD	O
2234	125.0	15cm	CD	O
2235	125.0	to	TO	O
2236	125.0	705.07m	CD	O
2237	125.0	.	.	O

2238	126.0	Lake	NNP	O
2239	126.0	Te	NNP	I-LOC
2240	126.0	Anau	NNP	I-LOC
2241	126.0	was	VBD	O
2242	126.0	at	IN	O
2243	126.0	202.5m	CD	O
2244	126.0	today	NNP	B-DATE
2245	126.0	,	,	O
2246	126.0	almost	RB	O
2247	126.0	1m	CD	O
2248	126.0	higher	JJR	O
2249	126.0	than	IN	O
2250	126.0	on	IN	O
2251	126.0	Monday	NNP	B-DATE
2252	126.0	,	,	O
2253	126.0	while	IN	O
2254	126.0	Lake	NNP	O
2255	126.0	Manapouri	NNP	B-LOC
2256	126.0	rose	VBD	O
2257	126.0	from	IN	O
2258	126.0	176.65m	CD	O
2259	126.0	to	TO	O
2260	126.0	177.53m	CD	O
2261	126.0	over	IN	O
2262	126.0	the	DT	O
2263	126.0	two	CD	O
2264	126.0	days	NNS	B-DATE
2265	126.0	.	.	O

2266	127.0	—	:	O
2267	127.0	NZPA	NNP	B-ORG
2268	127.0	.	.	O
